Guide to Samuel F.B. Morse Papers MC.10
New York University Archives
Samuel F.B. Morse Papers
1838-1985, undated
New York University Archives
Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872
Still, Bayrd
MC.10
0.67 Linear Feet in a manuscript box and half manuscript box
Scope and Contents
The Samuel F.B. Morse Collection contains inventories of letters from and about Morse; biographical summaries; papers relating to his career as an artist; his association with the University of the City of New York (now New York University); the invention of the telegraph and exhibitions thereof; and his experiments with photography. The collection also includes information on his will and his funeral; the Morse Plaque, which was placed on Main Building at NYU; the centennial celebration of his invention of the telegraph in 1944; the Morse Medal; and information concerning the Morse Telegraph Club, Inc.
The collection comprises one document box of material that serves as the primary reference file for the Archives staff on Morse. Additional material on Morse in the New York University Archives consists of nine letters in the Chancellors' Records, 1827-1885 (RG 3.0.1), newspaper reports on an address to the University alumni in 1853, and monographs about Morse.
The Samuel F.B. Morse Collection includes an essay on Morse and his association with New York University by Gary Reynolds, former curator of the Grey Art Gallery at NYU, that appeared in the catalog prepared for the Samuel F.B. Morse exhibition at New York University, September 14 to October 23, 1982; a folder listing of the Morse Collection; and a bibliography of works on Morse in the New York University Archives.
The collection also contains approximately 50 print photographs depicting topics related to Samuel Morse including awards, artistic renderings, patents, his telegraph, his trunk, and paintings that feature the telegraph.
Biographical Note
Samuel F.B. Morse was born in Charlestown, Mass., April 27, 1791. He began his association with the University of the City of New York (now New York University) at age 41. By this time he had an established reputation as an artist. Morse founded the National Academy of Design and presided over it since its inception in 1826. He lectured widely on art from 1826 to 1829. Morse left for Europe in 1829 and returned to New York in October, 1832. Within days he was appointed Chair of Sculpture and Painting at the University.
When the University Building on Washington Square opened in 1835, Morse rented space there for lodgings and to house a studio and laboratory for his experiments in photography and telegraphy. Morse left the University Building in 1841 but continued his association as professor of fine arts until his retirement in 1871. Although Morse's connection with the University has been described as "nominal," he maintained close contact with certain faculty members and emphasized his professorial connection. He died April 2, 1872, in New York.
Separated Materials
NYU's Fales Library contains 24 letters written by Morse between 1822 and 1870 (see Folder 1 of Morse Collection for inventory).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged at the folder level by subject.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research without restrictions.
Custodial History
In May 2025, approximately 50 print photographs depicting topics related to Samuel Morse was transferred from the New York University Archives Portrait Files (MC 319). The accession number associated with this accretion is 2025.022.
photoprints.; Photography; Clippings (information artifacts); Memorabilia.; Education -- Study and teaching -- United States; Biographies.; Art -- Study and teaching.; Inventions; Telegraph; Jones, Theodore Francis, 1885-1968; Morse, Herbert C.; Morse, Edward L.; New York University. Department of Fine Arts. Sculpture and Painting; New York University. School of Design; Morse Society; National Academy of Design (U.S.) (2017-); University of the City of New York; Nally, Edward Julian, 1859-1953; New York University -- Faculty -- 19th century
- Inventories of Morse letters and paintings at NYU, 1972-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Biographical summaries and notes, 1901-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Morse as artist, 1932-1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Morse's association with the University of the City of New York (now New York University), 1838-1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Invention of the telegraph and exhibitions thereof, 1838-1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Morse's experiments with photography, 1840-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Will and report of funeral--New York Times clipping, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Morse family: letter, Edward L. Morse to Miss [?] Solomons, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Morse Chair of Fine Arts at NYU: miseellaneous notes and Council minutes (excerpts), 1932-1935, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Morse Plaque or "tablet" on Main Building at NYU, 1932-1935, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Proposal of Morse celebration, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- E.J. Nally collection of Morse memorabilia, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Centennial celebration of 1844 demonstration of telegraph, May 14, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence of Theodore F. Jones (historian of NYU) re Morse, 1929-1946 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Samuel F.B. Morse Medal, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Morse Telegraph Club, Inc., 1942-1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Locust Grove: Young-Morse historic site, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Morse Society: correspondence with Herbert C Morse II, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Photographs -- Awards, Replicas, and Artistic Renderings, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Photographs -- "Westward the Nation" Painting, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Photographs -- Patent Papers, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Photographs -- Allegorical Landscape, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Photographs -- Traveling Trunk, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Photographs -- Invitation and Telegraph, 1932, 1940, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Photographs -- First Public Telegraph, circa 1836 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Photographs -- Samuel Morse and John Draper Exhibition Materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)